hi this is part 2 of the video tutorial
series
what is the magellan course in this
tutorial we are going to look at
dialectical reasoning through the work
of gebser in his notion of the
structures of consciousness in our last
tutorial we talked about the magellan
course be being interested in crossing a
frontier and that frontier was between
the current state where our reasoning is
dialectical has a dialectical dynamic
into a potential situation which is not
dialectical but represents a new way of
thinking that is not dialectical and so
I think it is important to understand
the evolution of dialectical reasoning
reasoning how it came to be what exactly
characterizes and accounts for
dialectical reasoning before we go on to
investigate the possibility of new types
of consciousness and new structures of
reasoning that do not operate
dialectically so we're going to look at
this today in terms of gaps or
structures of consciousness and gap sirs
work the ever-present origin and in the
subsequent videos part three we'll look
at dialectical reasoning through
developmental theory and in part four
we'll look at dialectical reasoning
through the history of philosophy but
for today we are going to look at
dialectical reasoning through gap sirs
work from the ever-present
origin his book the ever-present origin
and this notion of the evolution of the
structures of consciousness so
I hope you enjoy this tutorial gebser
saw the evolution of human consciousness
as proceeding through great epochal
shifts and he uses that term epic so if
we imagine three waves or three great
epochal shifts shifts ethics of
consciousness and the way he saw these
ethics arising were through phases so
each epoch would have a phase in the
phases would go from latent or the early
days to efficient phase the height of
the maturity of the essence of the
structure consciousness to a deficient
phase so we can think of this epoch here
between these two points as the epoch we
are in this epoch here as the epoch that
came before and so this you know just
before we start moving into our epoch
our structure of consciousness today we
would have come from the deficient stage
for the previous epoch and moving out of
our structure of consciousness
developing toward the new we move we'll
see we're moving into a new latent stage
of the new structure of consciousness
now each of these structures of
consciousness can be identified by the
types of reasoning that are evident
through works of art
through philosophy through language
through different cultural traditions
and structures and so what we're going
to look at today is the current
structure of consciousness over the last
2,000 years is called a mental structure
the previous structure of consciousness
gaps are called the mythic structure not
to be confused with the mythic level of
development within the mental structure
and the upcoming or the new structure of
consciousness gaps are called
integral again not to be confused with
the term integral in terms of
developmental theory within the mental
structure and we will look at
structure in the next video so each of
these epochs each of structures of
consciousness have a three phase kind of
evolutionary momentum within the mental
structure of consciousness that we are
in now delay in form of reasoning gaps
are called OSI yannick the efficient
form of reasoning gaps are called
pyramidal and we'll see why and the
deficient form a reason gaps are called
perspectival
and in general gifts are left these the
detail of the integral structure blank
and so this is the territory where we're
we're doing hypothetical work we're
trying to fill in the blanks in this
territory and they magellan course but
be consistent with some of the processes
that gaps are described now another
thing in in terms of what we're looking
at are these three types of reasoning
build up to what we understand as
dialectical reasoning so the movement
from the oceanic to the pyramidal to the
perspectival is a development of
dialectical reasoning through history
prior to this phase the mythic was was
not yet dialectical and in fact even
oceanic reasoning is not yet dialectical
and so our hypothesis and this would be
consistent with gebser
is that beyond the epoch of the mental
structure of consciousness the types of
reasoning would be no longer dialectical
so that's the hypothesis that we go from
the not yet dialectical epoch through
this process of the development of the
dialectical reasoning within this
evolutionary epic to a shift an
evolutionary shift to a new structure
consciousness the interval consciousness
trip structure of consciousness where it
is no longer dialectical and that would
be the reasoning behind the magellan
course trying to
look into this hypothetical territory to
give it more detail the way gebser has
detailed the reasoning structures as
they develop through the mental epoch
okay so that's basically the grand over
view so what we can do is parse out and
look at OSI Anik thinking for oceanic
reasoning oceanic reasoning was not
quite yet
dialectical and it proceeds from the
mythic and gaps are dismayed these
distinguished distinctions the mythic
he's called the mythic he called two
dimensional and the characteristic of a
mythical this would be the mythic
stepping back here the characteristic of
the mythical is that there was always a
return never a progression never never a
progression and so we see this in mythic
cultures today our mythical systems so
you have cycles seasonal cycles where
they're spraying their summer or there's
fall there's winter in their spring so
there's always a return a mandala like
mentality there's a the temperance or
the time frame is always cyclical or
periodic Zeus flew around the heavens in
a diurnal pattern there's tales of birth
and rebirth in cyclical patterns like
the pale of the Phoenix
so the mythic had this two-dimensional
character to it in the problem with the
mythic is that it represented in its
deficient stage just before the new
epoch the problem with the mythic is
that it became you know it was
completely closed that all the systems
had been completely closed within this
endless cycle of return so the cultural
structures the cultural systems the
power structures the kinds of
justifications human humans used for
moral and ethic jurisprudence they all
ended up having no ability to get beyond
this closure this is the way things are
they will always be the same there's no
there's no the illusion that things
change is defeated by the fact that
things always return so gaps are talked
about this this this problem with
closure of the system that created the
impetus or the dynamics for the mythic
type of reasoning this two dimensional
reasoning to move into a new type of
reasoning in the first indication of
that gebser calls oceanic reasoning
so if we look at Oceana Creason again
just to back up mythic wheezing and had
this polar structure so if this was the
beginning you reason you reason you come
back there's always a return and that
represented closure and the mythic style
of reasoning it's two dimensional so you
have two dimensional with the closure
and gaps are called this polar reasoning
in this closure represented an
evolutionary synth dynamics to move
toward new types of reasoning so we get
to oceanic reasoning which gaps are
called oceanic because it has wave-like
movements that have indications of
progression but that eventually our
recursive also return the way the polar
reasoning does but in this gap Xerces
the beginning of a movement away from
polar reasoning and so for example in
oceanic reasoning he uses a quote from
Heraclitus and the quote goes Souls
death becomes water water yeah
becomes earth so there's a sense that
there's a progression from one term to
the next and then a progression to
another term this is the wave-like
structure of oceanic but then the way
this quote ends is from Earth water from
water soul and so you see despite this
progression there's a real ooping back
to origin and so there is this is
oceanic thinking is the latent precursor
of dialectical thinking for the
efficient phase of the mental structure
of consciousness and so we go from
mythic which has got this closed two
dimensional but closed reasoning cycle
to oceanic with Gibbs which gives us
some indication of this progression to
other terms relating the beginning term
to other terms but with the completion
of the thought argument always going
still going back to close on the origin
still have as many valid like quality so
that's why he calls oceanic thinking
late in its it shows signs of moving
from polar reasoning in the mythic
structure but it's not quite yeah as
mature a dialectical process as the next
phase that get gaps are identifies in
the mental structure the development of
the mental structure of consciousness
into the efficient phase he calls that
thinking pyramidal so we go from the
polar reasoning of a mythic structure to
the transitional things oceanic and its
wave-like structure to the efficient
phase the pyramidal which today we
recognize as dialectical thinking and
certainly gebser did also
so now we'll turn to the efficient phase
of the mental structure and that's
pyramidal thinking okay so we are going
from the mythic to oceanic which is the
first indication of dialectical thinking
- pyramidal thinking caps are called the
mythic two dimensional with its closure
and he called pyramidal three
dimensional in the reason why is that
pyramidal thinking we won't be surprised
looks like this can be illustrated like
this you have a you have not a and then
you have a progression to a higher
synthesis so here's the origin airy term
it is contrasted with its opposite so at
the far end so if this is summer this
would be winter and instead of having a
completion in this argument Baptist to
summer this tension this gap is held
open in lieu of the search for a higher
synthesis in this higher that synthesis
gaps are talked about as the
third term for the tercio in this
pyramidal or triangular structure is
what gives this type of reasoning the
label pyramidal so now the interesting
thing is that pyramidal thinking in the
term dialectic comes from Plato and he
uses the term diuresis and what diuresis
means is separation and it refers to the
ability for the mind to hold this gap
this tension in this gap between
antinomies or opposites in order to
force a higher synthesis in order to
gain a higher synthesis and so you see
some of this in Plato and Socrates the
way Socrates would tease out the
paradoxes and force people to move to a
higher level of thinking and this paved
the way for all kinds of evolutionary
advances in human history
but this notion of being of diuresis of
being able to hold these antenna memes
as opposites at the end of a spectrum
was a significant difference than what
the mythic mind could do the mythic mind
would always see these categories as
turning over on themselves in the
MacDonald like fashion and just
recapitulating themselves
what we then see in terms of what
dialectical reasoning amounts to after
2,000 years of dialectical reasoning is
that you have this pyramidal thought
that leads to a higher synthesis which
then finds its antithesis if this leads
to a higher level synthesis and after
2,000 years the whole system has created
this very progressive or progression
this notion of reasoning as progress
progress or progression and gets it was
very careful and very pains taken to
note that this concept of progress or
progression is a product of a
dialectical style of reasoning of the
mental structure of consciousness and so
when he talks about the evolution of the
structures of consciousness he does not
mean to imply or to incorporate this
mental structure of progression on to
the notion of evolution this is very
important way important point in reading
gebser that our tendency to see
evolutionary processes as progressive is
merely a condition of the mental
structure of consciousness and so this
is another kind of view
that is conditional to and depended upon
the mental structure ethic of
consciousness and so forget sir because
he was moving beyond that conditions
mindset he saw evolutionary change as
just that epochal shift but not
necessarily progressive and that the
notion of progression is imputed on
epochal shift by the mental structure of
consciousness because of the dialectical
style of reasoning which over 2,000
years sees this constant progression in
the in analogous to the way the mythic
structure of consciousness saw
everything as complete iteration in
return the mental structure of
consciousness sees everything as
increasingly progressing and so we here
of the concept of complexification
complexification that systems and
evolution complexified over time and
this is merely a view of the mental
structure in its type of reasoning which
is gives us this progressive
understanding of epochal shift so Gibson
really worked hard at making these kinds
of distinctions so people could
understand that the way we view
evolution is a byproduct of the epoch
that we are in so without a doubt there
is this epochal shift but it it only
appears as a progressive
complexification a continual progression
in complexification because of the
dynamics the dialectical dynamics of a
mental structure and so this pyramidal
type of thinking with its positive
consequences results in some of its own
limitations represents the efficient
phase of the mental structure of
consciousness and the really the epoch
we've been in for the last two thousand
years now the questions we are in the
pyramidal or efficient stage phase of
the mental structure and we even gaps I
could see that this had already begun to
become deficient or we could say it had
it started to exhaust its useful
evolutionary usefulness as it moved into
what he called the deficient stage and
he associates that with his term for
that his perspective table now this is
very interesting because if you're
familiar with integral theory or aqua
theory then the whole notion of
perspective ilysm and Multan integral
methodological pluralism and
multi-perspective ilysm is touted as the
pinnacle of rational development in but
for the very same reasons that gebser
saw what perspectival reasoning was he
sees that he codifies this as the
deficient stage of the
mental structure so there's actually a
complete disconnect between aqua theory
and gassers notion of the perspectival
phase gebser saw the perspectival phase
of reasoning in the mental structure as
being deficient so this is a not a small
point if you are a scholar of integral
theory is aqua aqua version of integral
theory so why did gaps or sea
perspective ilysm as being deficient
well it's quite you know gap stirred
himself is quite complicated to read but
what I can summarize for you is that
after 2000 years of this progressive
movement to find the third term there
are three major reasons why the pinnacle
of this which is prospective ilysm is
become deficient and number one is is
that the perspectival ism is developed
because of 2,000 years of meta
theoretical division so you have higher
in high the third term represents higher
and higher levels of integration but the
situation is so complexified and so
driven by this notion of progress in
higher higher levels
that the that the there are no so there
they're no longer and any solutions okay
the solutions the inquiries become more
and more abstract more and more meta
theoretical more and more complexified
they can't solve any it doesn't solve
any more problems so in a sense it
represents a closure so they're the meta
frames that are required these are not
get search terms itself represents the
kind of closure because you're
constantly moving to more and more
complex higher abstract versions of the
inquiry and so that's why he called this
phase deficient the second reason is
because the meta frames these are not
his terms this is a synopsis they exit
their own domain the domain of inquiry
so for example in Hargens and
Zimmerman's book integral ecology they
it's a compendium of hundreds of
different approaches to ecology parsed
out based upon altitude this notion of
altitude worldview the who the what the
where that it makes all these
perspective distinctions but when you
read the book interval ecology it does
not do ecology okay it does meta theory
and so the problem with perspective
ilysm is that it it creates its own map
territory confusion the map becomes so
complex
you're so concerned with the map in its
ever increasing complexity that you
really kind of lost touch with being and
this is really the critique that gaps
are has with perspective ilysm and that
is that all these progressive shifts in
the pyramidal structure of reasoning
after two thousand years has created a
transit idea of transcendence as truth
and has completely lost touch is made a
gap this gap that's being held between
has been iterated over and over and over
again so now there's this complete gap
between this transcendent abstraction
and what he would call being or origin
in that perspective ilysm and meta
theory can no longer get at imminence
and the basic fundamental ground of
being so this is really the biggest
critique about perspective ilysm that it
starts to be distracted by its own
abstractions and it no longer what gaps
or can't uses the coins of term no
longer a where's the truth in being and
so what was once in the pyramidal form
efficient and evolutionarily
advantageous has become in the
perspectival form deficient and the only
place I see this in aqua theory is when
Wilbur says that aqua is a map of the
prison and this really would resonate
with gebser
that perspectival ism is a great map but
it's a map of the prison and the prison
been generated by dialectical mind the
prison is nothing but the rarefied
abstractions of dialectical mind and so
this represents what gaps would call the
deficient phase of the mental structure
of consciousness which is this hyper
complexified dialectical reasoning so
we've moved from the mythic and it's
polar reasoning which is not yet
dialectic to the mental structure of
consciousness in its three phases the
latent phase and the latent phase which
is ocn ik reasoning the efficient phase
which is pyramidal and the deficient
phase which is perspectival and so now
we want to look at what is the latent
phase of the new structure
one of the types of reasoning that gets
her sees as a candidate we just call it
a candidate for this latent phase of the
new structure he called paradoxical
reasoning and paradoxical reasoning has
this can be described as being able to
hold this gap of a and not eight let's
say so can still hold this gap so in
that sense it retains some of the
experience of diuresis or separation but
what it does is it resists the synthetic
synthetic move-move or the tree resists
the synthetic or the transcendent or
abstraction the higher abstraction
moving and that's what it calls it
paradoxical because it kind of rests in
this paradoxical territory just as that
without the synthetic move and what gaps
are saw it I think it's consistent with
what we see today the reason why this
alternative comes up is because the the
people that are starting to in the
history of what gebser was looking at
starting to reason in a more paradoxical
style or all people related to either
spirituality so for example the Buddhist
scholastics or that have some kind of
reinvent with being as a as for example
Heidegger or are interested in theology
or religion and so you have the
beginning of the Western process
philosophers and so this commonality
between them is that they were looking
outside the mind or beyond the mind to
ground the truth in being and in that
being in that experience of being they
found the ability to hold the mind
stable in this paradoxical state and so
paradoxical reasoning is a transitional
phase that gets our saw associated with
a movement that was not toward the
deficient phase of the mental structure
but he saw it as a transitional phase he
doesn't quite tag it as the latent phase
of the new structure but he does
identify paradoxical reasoning in a
category of its own entrance
transitional between dialectical
reasoning it has this ability to hold
this paradox but resisting this tendency
to make the higher synthetic move
creates a completely different view and
so
that is an important phase to consider
as we continue our inquiry in the
magellan course